Stephen, so let let me ask you a
question and maybe we can we can go
this. So the issue that I'm still having
with my patients on any it's acne and we
tend to see a lot of acne on our
patients. So what we do with our
patients of course the cleaner you eat
the better you tend to do. We try to
improve their gut health. Um if we see
acne we'll kind of do to decrease the
peak. So we'll go three times a week
micro doing daily but we have some
patients no matter everything we do they
still have acne. What do you do with
your patients that you you see acne on
TRT? Yeah I I I love to go directly to
esoterinuine that's Accutane and us but
I'd like to uh give very small dosing.
So a micro doing um eotinoin like only
10 milligrams a day that's very well
tolerated minimal side effects just
maybe a bit of dry lips and after a
while it takes a while to build up
because uh the it's compounding the dose
in your system but after a few months it
gives really good effects on acne and
especially if you go up to 100 to 150
milligrams per kilogram of body
um you tend to get off uh your acne for
always. So after this accumulated dose
100 150 milligrams per kilogram uh you
can just stop it and um yeah be forever
without your acne. So I see that in a
lot of patients if they are on TRT or
not. Sometimes I I get men from 40 years
old still with cistic acne and even with
micro doing esoterin but that can take
up to one year and a half two years at
that dose but eventually they're uh can
they can stop. Amazing. Yes, that that's
what I've done with some of my patients.
you know there's a fear of Accutane
because of the liver toxicity but at the
low do like you said we monitor the
levels I haven't seen any liver toxicity
so I didn't know that micro doing so 10
milligram a day and you give it time
yeah you just give it time to build it
up up to 100 150 milligrams per kilogram
of body weight so that can take up to 18
24 months at that dose but hey after a
few weeks it will already start to get
better And as you say, toxicity it's
just dose dependent. It's like having
alcohol beverages. If you take just one
a week, it's no problem. If you have
four each day, uh that will hurt your
liver as well. So at 10 milligrams, even
if you do blood exams once in a while,
you never see any liver changes in the
enzymes of our liver. Very good. What
about the use of antibiotics like
doxycyc? Usually what I do, I'll do a
course of doxycyc first and a lot of
patients improve with this. And if they
don't then I'll do the yakutane. Tell me
about your use of of antibiotics with
acne patients. Yeah, the problem with
antibiotics is always the same in most
men and women and teenagers. They work,
but as soon as you stop, the acne comes
back. So I I've seen young adults
telling me, "Oh, I've been
on my
orthroycline, whatever. I've been taking
them for five years and I can't stop
because when I stop everything comes
back. It's much healthier to do one year
of micro doing esoterinino than five
years of minocy. So the antibiotics they
work fine sometimes quicker and without
any side effects but you can't get off
them. It will all just come back the
acne. Wow amazing pearls. Thank you
Stephen. Do you ever combine them maybe
to do the minocycine for a little bit to
kind of get it to go away quickly? No,
it's it's
contraindicated the the cichlines. So
the the antibiotics that are most
indicated for acne, you cannot combine
them with the retinoids
likeinoine because there's a rare side
effect when you combine these um intra
cranial hypertension. That's one risk if
you combine those. So it's a no-go. Very
good. So it seems what's the usual
typical dose of acute of the tininoine
because 10 milligram is micro dose.
What's the usual dose that I see they
use usually? Oh, you you can go up to
your body weight in kilograms. So if you
weigh 70 kilos, you can titrate up to 70
milligrams a day. But that's very heavy
on the liver, on the lips, dry skin
everywhere. So um if we do a good dose
and you want it if you have if you have
um a good young liver you you don't take
any other medications you don't drink
alcohol at all I sometimes give people
half of their body weight like 60 no 30
40 milligrams that's just a normal dose
and with that dose you will get up to
your accumulated um 100 150 in six
months time and then you can stop
amazing and then maybe the 10 milligram
if you're even more worried but you stay
micro dose but long term. Yeah. Yeah.
Perfect man. This is look at this. This
is this is the dermatologist. Well, who
else can give such great advice? I will
bring that back to my patients. Thank
you. Yeah. Sure. Sure. I I have over
Yeah. 22 years of um clinical practice
now. So I've been doing this every day
for the last two decades. Yes. Yes. Yes.
Are there any acne washes that you like?
any of the benzoxil preparation.
Yeah, we have a lot of salicylic acid,
benzoic acid type containing uh
cleansers, those standard things. But
once once you get on isotriinoin, you
don't have to use those anymore because
they will dry out your skin even more.
So you just wash yourself with a very
gentle wash once on retinoids. But if
you don't take or but if you are not
taking retinoids just antibiotics oral
antibiotics for example then you try to
dry out your sibic skin with one of
those washes salicylic acid benzoic acid
there are others. Perfect. Thank you
Stephen. You're welcome, Frzy.
[Music]